A Finding Aid to the Ida Jervis Papers, 1951-1996, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Ida Jervis papers
1951-1996
Archives of American Art
Jervis, Ida
AAA.jervida
Archival Resource Key
2.6 Linear feet
The papers of photographer and puppeteer Ida Jervis measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1951 to 1996. Found are files concerning Washington D.C. area artists, collectors, exhibitions, festivals, institutions and museums.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Scope and Contents
The papers of photographer and puppeteer Ida Jervis measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1951 to 1996. Found are files concerning Washington D.C. area artists, collectors, exhibitions, festivals, institutions and museums.
Files may include printed material, photographs, biographical material, and correspondence. Additionally, three scrapbooks contain photographs and clippings from Jervis's career as a photographer and writer for local Washington, D.C. newspapers.
Existence and Location of Copies
Material lent for microfilming is available on 35mm microfilm reel 4973 available at Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Separated Materials
The Archives of American Art also holds microfilm of a scrapbook containing printed material and photographs taken by Ida Jervis of the Now Festival held in Washington, D.C., April 26 to May 1, 1966, on Reel 4973. Originals were returned to the lender, Ida Jervis, after microfilming and are not described in the collection container inventory.
Biographical / Historical
Ida Jervis (1917-2014) was a photographer, puppeteer, and writer in Washington, D.C. Jervis's photographs were featured in The Jewish Week of Washington and other publications.
Ida Goodstein Jervis was born in Poland in 1917 and immigrated to the United States in 1921, where she settled in Tennessee. She married Sidney Jervis and relocated to Northern Virginia outside of Washington, D.C. in 1944. In the 1960s, Jervis's writings and photographs appeared in local Washington D.C. newspapers. Her work often centered around the D.C. area arts scene. Additionally, she was an avid puppeteer and was active with the National Capital Puppetry Guild.
Ida Jervis died in 2014 in Falls Church, Virginia.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ida Jervis donated a portion of her papers in 1994. Her daughter, Margie Jervis, donated additional papers in 2014
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Art festivals; Artists -- Washington D.C. -- Photographs; Artists -- Washington Metropolitan Area -- Photographs; Women artists; Photographers -- Washington (D.C.); Women photographers; Scrapbooks; Puppeteers -- Washington (D.C.); Authors -- Washington (D.C.); Women authors; Now Festival (1966: Washington, D.C.)
- Ida Jervis Papers, 1951-1956; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 2.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-4
  Scope and Contents
  The bulk of Ida Jervis's files concern artists, arts organizations, collectors, exhibitions, festivals, institutions and museums in and around Washington, D.C. Files may contain printed material, photographs, biographical material, and correspondence. Of note are files kept on Samuel Bookatz, Hadassah Art Collectors Show, Israel Room at the Kennedy Center, Jack Perlmutter, Prentiss Taylor, and Alma Thomas.
  Three scrapbooks date from the 1960s to the 1970s and include clippings and photographs relating to Jervis's articles for The Alexandria Gazette, The Jewish Week, and The Arlington and Alexandria Globe, and concerning her puppetry activities.
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically by name or subject.
  - Abraham, Rachel, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abramson, Ann and Ronald, 1982-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aden, Alonzo, 1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Americas, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amram, David, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arlington Art Center, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Art Barn, Opening, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Art Scene Magazine, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1971-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Artists, Photographs and Resumes, 1960-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Artists, Photographs and Resumes (Oversized, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Asher, Lila Oliver, 1951-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Associated Counsel for the Arts, Conference, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Awret, Azriel and Irene, 1967-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bader, Franz, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Benson, Anne, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Berkowitz, Leon, 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bermudez, Jose, 1966-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bleifeld, Stanley, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bluestone, Abraham, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Bookatz, Samuel, 1950-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Bruskin, Kathleen, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Calfee, William, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Chieffo, Clifford, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Chihuly, Dale, 1978-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cohen, Lois, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Collectors and Patrons, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cooke, Hereward Lester, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Corcoran Gallery of Art, 1968-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Cordini, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Danzansky, Tina, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Dean, Andrea Cohen, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Dempsey, Richard, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Dupont Center--Washington Gallery of Modern Art, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Edelman, Ann, 1961-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Emerson Gallery, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Exhibit 69, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Frank, Phoebe, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Gallery Watchers, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Gambaro, Retna Walden, 1976-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Goldberg, Margery, 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Hadassah Art Collectors Show, 1966-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Hadl, Robin H., circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Halprin, Ann, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Hirshhorn, Joseph, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Hirshhorn Museum, 1969-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49-50)
  - Howard University, Faculty, 1969-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Hufford, Caroline, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - International Monetary Fund Gallery, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
  - Irvine, John, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Israel Room, Kennedy Center, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 56-58)
  - Jervis, Ida, 1951-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jervis, Margie, 1966-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Kainen, Jacob, 1967-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Kapos, June, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Kienholz, Ed, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - King Street Coop Studio, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Knight, Jennie Lea, 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - KOAN (Ken Oda's Art Newsletter), 1993-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lachman, Mildred, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lazzari, Pietro, 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Lee, Edna, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Levine, Helen, 1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Levitine, Dr. George, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Loewinger, Lenore, 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mauer, Leonard, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Max, Peter, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - McAdams, Alfred, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - McBryde, Sara "Missy", 1971-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Milligan, Joan, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Mitchell, Miriam, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Moore, Keiko Hiratsuka, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - National Council on the Arts and Government, 1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Newman, Elias, circa 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Newman, Maurice, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Now Festival, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Orsinger, Mike, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - P Street NW, Party, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Parsons, Jenny, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Patrick Lannon Foundation, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Perlman, Herman, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Perlmutter, Jack, 1955-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Pierce, Delilah, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Porta, Guilio, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Possony, Vally T, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Ratner, Phillip, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Rauschenberg, Robert, 1966, 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Russo, Alexander, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Schaefer, Rita, 1967-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Scheele, Carl and John, 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Scrapbooks, 1966-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook, 1966-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Shanklin, Maxine, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Sickman, Jessalee, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Simkin, Shayna, 1968-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Smithsonian Institution, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Street Art, Washington, D.C., 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Taylor, Prentiss, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Thomas, Alma, circa 1966-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Twitty, James, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Wanveer, Tad, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Washington Art Dealers Association, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Washington Artists Today, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Wertheim, Anita, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - White, Robert, 1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Winslow, John, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Woodward, William, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Wright, Frank, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Zapolski, Edward, 1967-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 57)